<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.2/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.2/sch/docbook.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<article version="5.1" 
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Editing and writing in DocBook XML</title>
    <subtitle>Hackweek 21</subtitle>
    <info>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Tom</firstname>
                <surname>Schraitle</surname>
            </personname>
            <email>toms@suse.de</email>
        </author>
        <pubdate>2022-06-30</pubdate>
        <abstract>
            <para>
                Our documentation format of choice is DocBook XML.
                We heard people saying that it is <quote>too complicated</quote>
                or <quote>too complex</quote>. But it has many advantages. And if
                you understand the way of tagging, it is no rocket science anymore.
                The purpose of this session is to enable you to edit documentation
                sources written in DocBook yourself, or to even write/contribute content.
            </para>
        </abstract>
    </info>

    <section>
        <title>Requirements</title>
        <para>
            Bascially, you need:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Editor, preferably supports XML</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>XML toolchain</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Editors</title>
        <para>Bascially, any (text) editor will work. However, you have to add those
            tags manually. That can be very cumbersome. There are a few open source XML
            editors you can use:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Emacs</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Vim</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>VSCode</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            You need to configure them properly. For example, you could create recurring
            snippets that you use very often. Or to use a schema file. This is outside of
            this session. If you are interested in this, ask the doc team, they can help you.
        </para>
        <para>
            There are other, more advanced, but commerical XML editors. If you want to try
            these, I'd recommend:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><link xlink:href="http://www.xmlmind.com/xmleditor"></link>XMLMind</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><link xlink:href="https://www.oxygenxml.com/">oXygen XML</link></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="xml-toolchain">
        <title>XML toolchain</title>
        <para>
            An XML toolchain allows you to do the two most important tasks when working
            with DocBook:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Validating your document against a schema</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Transforming your document into a target format (HTML, PDF, ...)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            Of course, it's not limited to these tasks. Depending on your toolchain and how it
            is configured, it could offer you additional tasks like to check all links or to perform
            a spellcheck.
        </para>
        <para>
            For using a XML toolchain, you could use one of these:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Minimal XML toolchain</title>
                    <para>Install the following packages:</para>
                </formalpara>
                <screen>sudo zypper install libxslt-tools libxml2-tools jing \
  docbook5-xsl-stylesheets docbook_5 xmlgraphics-fop</screen>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Comfortable XML toolchain (recommended):</title>
                    <para>Install the following packages:</para>
                </formalpara>
                <screen>sudo zypper install daps daps2docker</screen>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>DocBook's philosophy</title>
        <para>
            DocBook cares about "semantic", the meaning of a particular
            object. The layout is something of second nature and added later.
        </para>
        <para>
            That's why you find in DocBook tag names like <tag>filename</tag> or
            <tag>example</tag> to help the author to markup their text.
            You won't find tag names like bold, italic, underline, or other
            layout information.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>DocBook schemas and versions</title>
        <para>
            Currently, there are two main versions in use:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Version 4.x</title>
                    <para>
                        This is the old version that you can find on some
                        legacy documents.
                        You won't see any major improvements except bugfixes.
                    </para>
                </formalpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Version 5.x (recommended)</title>
                    <para>
                        This is the current version. Any development happens
                        here. If you want to be up-to-date with the latest
                        DocBook schema and be more future-safe, use this version.
                    </para>
                </formalpara>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            DocBook is a <emphasis>schema</emphasis>. The DocBook schema defines the
            DocBook element and attribute names and their parent-child relationships.
            For example, you can't have a <tag>title</tag> tag without, for example, a
            <tag>chapter</tag> tag as parent.
            The DocBook schema defines not only their names and structure them, it
            defines also the cardinality (how many tags you can use) and in which order
            is allowed.
        </para>
        <para>
            The DocBook schema itself is just a concept. To work with that, you need
            a <emphasis>schema file</emphasis>. Unfortunately, the DocBook schema file(s)
            comes in different formats. In most cases, the two most important formats are:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Document Type Definitions (DTD)</title>
                    <para>
                        This is a very old format and was definied together with XML.
                        It is mainly used for DocBook version 4.x.
                    </para>
                </formalpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>RELAX NG (RNG)</title>
                    <para>
                        This is a more modern format. It is used for DocBook
                        version 5.x exclusively.
                    </para>
                </formalpara>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Working with DocBook documents</title>
        <para>
            As said before in <xref linkend="xml-toolchain"/>, the two main tasks for
            a XML toolchain are:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Validating</title>
                    <para>
                        This means, checking your documents against the rules defined
                        in the DocBook RELAX NG schema.
                    </para>
                </formalpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <formalpara>
                    <title>Transforming</title>
                    <para>
                        This means, converting your DocBook document into a target
                        format. To do this, you need the DocBook XSL stylesheets.
                        These stylesheets are able to convert your DocBook document
                        into (X)HTML, PDF, and a few other formats.
                        It is even possible to customize the DocBook XSL stylesheets
                        or write your own if you want to support other, unsupported formats.
                    </para>
                </formalpara>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <section>
            <title>Choosing DocBook elements</title>
            <para>
                DocBook is a format for writing technical documentation.
                It's based on XML, so all the rules for XML apply to DocBook
                as well.
            </para>
            <para>
                DocBook consists of roughly 400 elements. Don't worry, you won't
                need all of them. These elements are sorted into three categories:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Division elements:</title>
                        <para>
                            structure your documents into book, article, chapter,
                            section, etc.
                        </para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Block elements</title>
                        <para>
                            are greater building blocks like example, table, figure,
                            procedure etc.
                        </para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Inline elements</title>
                        <para>
                            for the more tiny things to markup; usually inside
                            paragraphs and other block elements.
                            For example, command, filename, quote, etc.
                        </para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Metadata elements</title>
                        <para>
                            elements which may or may not appear in your target
                            format. Normally acts as <quote>metadata</quote>.
                            Usually everything that you can find inside
                            <tag>info</tag>.
                        </para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>
                When you create your document, you start with one division element
                as root element. Depending on your structure, you add more
                division elements. Add block elements inside your division elements.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Validating DocBook documents</title>
            <para>
                If you write in DocBook 5.x, use the command <command>jing</command> to
                validate your document like this (replace <replaceable>XML_FILE</replaceable>
                with the file name of your DocBook document):
            </para>
            <screen>jing /usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/rng/5.2/docbook.rng <replaceable>XML_FILE</replaceable></screen>
            <para>
                If everything was fine, you won't get any output (<quote>no news are good news</quote>).
                In case something is wrong with your XML file, you get an error message pointing
                to the problem:
            </para>
            <screen>article.xml:212:5: fatal: The end-tag for element type "screen" must end with a '>' delimiter.</screen>
            
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Transforming DocBook documents</title>
            <para>
                To <quote>consume</quote> your document, after you have successfully validated it,
                you can transform it into your target format. For this example, we use HTML5.
            </para>
            <screen>xsltproc --output article.html \
    /usr/share/xml/docbook/stylesheet/nwalsh5/current/xhtml5/docbook.xsl \
    article.xml</screen>
            <para>
                Point your browser to the file <filename>article.html</filename>.
            </para>
            <para>
                Keep in mind, if your DocBook document has a syntax error, the whole process
                stops. The transformation can only be executed if your file is syntactically
                correct.
                Your file should also be <emphasis>valid</emphasis>. Although you could
                transform an invalid file, the result will be possibly wrong.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Further information</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <link xlink:href="https://tdg.docbook.org/tdg/5.2/">DocBook reference documentation</link>
                    (TDG, The Definitive Guide)
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <link xlink:href="https://github.com/openSUSE/geekodoc">GeekoDoc</link>,
                    a customization of DocBook for SUSE documentation
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <link xlink:href="https://github.com/openSUSE/daps2docker/">daps2docker</link>,
                    everything delivered in a container
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <link xlink:href="https://opensuse.github.io/daps/">DAPS User Guide</link>
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
</article>
